A Guide to the Wickliffe Rose Papers FA032
Rockefeller Archive Center
Wickliffe Rose papers
1890-1933
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rose, Wickliffe (1862-1931)
Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease
Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division
General Education Board (New York, N.Y.)
International Education Board
Rockefeller Foundation
FA032
1.14 Cubic Feet 3 letter document cases
Arrangement note
This collection is divided into four series:
Series 1 - Tennessee
Series 2 - Rockefeller Interests
Series 3 - Personal Interests
Series 1035 - Photographs
Biographical/Historical note
Wickliffe Rose was born in Saulsbury, Tennessee, on November 19, 1862. He graduated from the University of Nashville in 1889 and received an A.M. degree from the University in 1890.
His career is divided by two major interests and two main associations. The first interest is that of education. Dr. Rose was instructor in history and mathematics at Peabody College from 1891-1892, and then professor of history and philosophy of education at that college from 1892-1902. In 1902 Dr. Rose moved to the faculty of the University of Tennessee where again he was professor of history and philosophy of education. From 1904-1907 he was Dean of Peabody College and the University of Nashville. In 1908 Dr. Rose left academic life, and he joined the Peabody Education Fund as General Agent in 1910. He also served as Executive Secretary for the Southern Education Board during 1909-1910.
Dr. Rose's second major interest was public health and, more specifically, public health education. In 1910 he turned down a position as President at Peabody College to become Executive Secretary of the Rockefeller Sanitary Commission until its termination in 1915. With the end of the Commission, Dr. Rose joined the International Health Division of the Rockefeller Foundation and extended the work of the Sanitary Commission to foreign countries, conducted a campaign against yellow fever, and promoted public health at home and abroad.
Resigning the Directorship of the International Health Division in 1923, Dr. Rose assumed the Presidency of the General Education Board and the International Education Board where he remained until his retirement in 1928.
Wickliffe Rose died on September 5, 1931, while on a fishing trip in British Columbia.
Scope and Contents note
Important subjects in this collection include Rose's election to Peabody College Presidency, Peabody Fund Award, International Health Division, travels, and fishing.
Among the correspondents are Victor G. Heiser; Abraham Flexner; George Clarke; Trevor Arnett; John D. Rockefeller, Jr.; A. E. Shipley; Wickliffe Rose; Frederick T. Gates; and John Ferrell.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers of Wickliffe Rose were deposited with The Rockefeller Foundation Archives in December 1966 and October 1968, by Harold Wickliffe Rose.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Tennessee
- Tennessee, 1902-1910; 1; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
  Scope and Contents note
  Series 1 includes material from Dr. Rose's days in Tennessee and his affiliations with Peabody College and the University of Nashville. The period roughly covers the years 1902-1910. Much of the material consists of letters to Dr. Rose in appreciation for the work he did as an educator.
  - Correspondence, 1902-1903 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1905-1906 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, January-July 6, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, July 7-20, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Peabody Education Fund, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Rockefeller Interests, 1910-1928; 2; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
  Series 2 contains a record of Dr. Rose's association with the Rockefeller Sanitary Commission, the International Health Division, the General Education Board and the International Education Board. It spans the years 1910-28.
  - Correspondence, 1910-1912 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1913-1914 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1917-1923 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1924-1928 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Diary, 1909-1910 (Box 1, Folder 9A)
  - Ordre National de la Legion d'Honneur, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Passports, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Personal Interests, undated; 3; 0.76 Cubic Feet 2 letter document boxes
  Series 3 is largely of the period of Dr. Rose's retirement after 1928. The material included in this series is of a personal nature. There are poems, exercises in French, notes on fishing, family correspondence and other similar material.
  - George H. Clarke, 1911-1918 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Family Correspondence, 1916-1933 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Fishing, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - French Exercises, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Memorabilia, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "My Father's People 1650-1958", undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Notes, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Poems and Stories, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Travel, 1928-1931 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, September 1931 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, October 1931-1932 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Telegrams, 1931-1932 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Harold W. Rose Inventory, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Wickliffe Rose photographs, 1035; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
  Photographs
  - Wickcliffe Rose (Box 14, Folder 178)